In System D, this
في نظام "د"، هذا
is a store,
إنه متجر
and what I mean by that is that this is a photograph
وما أعنيه بهذا أن هذه صورة
I took in Makoko, shantytown in Lagos, Nigeria.
إلتقطتها في ماكوكو، مدن الصفيح في لاغوس، نيجيريا
It's built over the lagoon, and there are no streets
إنها مبنية على البحيرة، وليس هناك أية شوارع
where there can be stores to shop,
حيث يمكن أن يكون هناك متاجر للتسوق
and so the store comes to you.
وبالتالي فإن المتجر يأتي إليك
And in the same community,
وفي نفس المجتمع
this is business synergy.
هذا تضافر الأعمال
This is the boat that that lady was paddling around in,
هذا هو القارب الذي كانت السيدة تجدف به في جميع الأنحاء،
and this artisan makes the boat and the paddles
وهذا الماهر يصنع القارب والمجاديف
and sells directly
ويبيع مباشرة
to the people who need the boat and the paddles.
للناس التي تحتاج القارب والمجاديف
And this is a global business.
وهذه تجارة عالمية
Ogandiro smokes fish in Makoko in Lagos,
أوقانديرو تدخن السمك في ماكوكوفي لاغوس
and I asked her, "Where does the fish come from?"
وسألتها "من أين أتى السمك؟"
And I thought she'd say, "Oh, you know,
وأظن أنها ستقول، "آه أنت تعرف
up the lagoon somewhere, or maybe across Africa,"
من مكان ما في البحيرة، أوقد يكون عبر أفريقيا"
but you'll be happy to know she said
ولكن ستكون سعيدا بمعرفتك أنها قالت
it came from here, it comes from the North Sea.
إنها أتت من هنا، إنها تأتي من البحر الشمالي
It's caught here, frozen, shipped down to Lagos,
إنها تُصطاد هنا، تجمد، تُشحن الى لاغوس
smoked, and sold for a tiny increment of profit
تدخّن وتباع بمقدار ضئيل من الربح
on the streets of Lagos.
في شوارع لاغوس
And this is a business incubator.
وهذه حاضنة أعمال
This is Olusosun dump, the largest garbage dump in Lagos,
هذا هو مطرح إوليوسوسن، وأكبر مكب للقمامة في لاغوس
and 2,000 people work here, and I found this out
وهنا يعمل 2000 شخص، وقد اكتشفت ذلك
from this fellow, Andrew Saboru.
من هذا الزميل، أندرو سوبرو.
Andrew spent 16 years scavenging materials on the dump,
أندريو قضى 16 سنة في جمع الفضلات من المطرح
earned enough money to turn himself into a contract scaler,
ربح أموالاً كافية لتحويله الى متعاقد
which meant he carried a scale and went around and
ما يعني أنه يحمل ميزاناً ويحوم
weighed all the materials that people had scavenged
لوزن كل المواد التي يجمعها الناس
from the dump. Now he's a scrap dealer.
من القمامة، هو الآن تاجر خردة.
That's his little depot behind him,
هذا هو مستودعه المتواضع خلفه
and he earns twice the Nigerian minimum wage.
وهو يربح ضعف الحد الأدنى للأجور في نيجيريا
This is a shopping mall.
هذا مجمع تجاري.
This is Oshodi Market in Lagos.
هذا هو سوق أوشودي في لاغوس
Jorge Luis Borges had a story called "The Aleph,"
جورج لويس بورغيس لديه قصة تسمى " الأليف"
and the Aleph is a point in the world
والأليف هي نقطة في العالم
where absolutely everything exists,
حيث أنه حتما كل شي موجود
and for me, this image is a point in the world
وبالنسبة لي، إن هذه الصورة هي نقطة في العالم
So, what am I talking about when I talk about System D?
لذا، ما اتحدث عنه عندما أتكلم عن النظام "د" ؟
It's traditionally called the informal economy,
إنه تقليدياً يسمى بالاقتصاد الغير الرسمي
the underground economy, the black market.
الاقتصاد المخفي، السوق السوداء
I don't conceive of it that way.
أنا لا أتصور الأمر على هذا النحو
I think it's really important to understand that something like
أنا أعتقد أنه فعلا مهم لفهم أن شيء مثل
this is totally open. It's right there for you to find.
هذا هو مفتوح تماماً. إنه موجود هناك ليتم اكتشافه
All of this is happening openly, and aboveboard.
كل هذا يحدث بانفتاح وعلانية
There's nothing underground about it.
لا شيء سري بخصوص هذا
It's our prejudgment that it's underground.
إنه حكمنا المبدئي بأن هذا سري
I've pirated the term System D from the former French colonies.
إني أقرصن مبدأ نظام "د" من المؤسس فرانك كولونيس
There's a word in French that is débrouillardise,
هناك كلمة واحدة باللغة الفرنسية وهي "débrouillardise" وتعني سعة الحيلة
that means to be self-reliant,
بمعنى أن تعتمد على ذاتك
and the former French colonies have turned that into
والمستعمرات الفرنسية السابقة قد حولت ذلك إلى
System D for the economy of self-reliance,
النظام "د" للاقتصاد ذي الاعتماد الذاتي
or the DIY economy.
أواقتصاد DIY (أفعلها بنفسك)
But governments hate the DIY economy,
ولكن الحكومة كرهت اقتصاد DIY
and that's why -- I took this picture in 2007,
ولهذا فأنا التقطت هذه الصورة في 2007
and this is the same market in 2009 --
وهذا هو نفس السوق في 2009
and I think, when the organizers of this conference
وأنا أظن، إذا كان منظمو هذا المؤتمر
were talking about radical openness,
يتحدثون عن الانفتاح الجذري
they didn't mean that the streets should be open
لم يقصدوا بذلك بذلك أن الشوارع يجب أن تكون مفتوحة
and the people should be gone.
وأن الناس يجب أن تذهب.
I think what we have is a pickle problem.
أعتقد بأن ما لدينا هي مشكلة مخللات
I had a friend who worked at a pickle factory,
لدي صديق يعمل في مصنع مخلّل
and the cucumbers would come flying down
والخيار يأتي نازلا عبر
this conveyer belt, and his job was to pick off the ones
الحزام الناقل وكانت وظيفته التقاط الخيارات
that didn't look so good and throw them in the bin
التي لا تبدوجيدة جداً ورميها في سلة مهملات
labeled "relish" where they'd be crushed and mixed
مكتوب عليها "منكّهة"حيث تسحق وتخلط
with vinegar and used for other kinds of profit.
مع الخل وتستخدم في منافع أخرى
This is the pickle economy.
هذا هو الاقتصاد المخلل
We're all focusing on — this is a statistic from
حيث جميعا نركز على - وهذه احصائية من
earlier this month in the Financial Times —
وقت سابق من هذا الشهر في صحيفة فاينانشال تايمز -
we're all focusing on the luxury economy.
نحن جميعا نركز على الاقتصاد الفاخر
It's worth 1.5 trillion dollars every year, and that's
إنه يقدر بحوالي 1.5 تريليون دولار سنويا، وهذا
a vast amount of money, right?
مبلغ كبير من المال، أليس كذلك؟
That's three times the Gross Domestic Product of Switzerland.
هذا هو ثلاثة أضعاف الناتج المحلي الإجمالي لسويسرا.
So it's vast. But it should come with an asterisk,
إنه ضخم ولكن يجب أن تأتي مصحوبة بهامش،
and the asterisk is that it excludes two thirds of the workers
والهامش هو أنه يستبعد ثلثي العمال
of the world.
من العالم
1.8 billion people around the world work
يعمل حوالي 1.8 مليار نسمة في العالم
in the economy that is unregulated and informal.
في الاقتصاد الغير المنظم وغير الرسمي
That's a huge number, and what does that mean?
وهذا عدد هائل، وماذا يعني ذلك؟
Well, it means if it were united in a single political system,
حسنا، هذا يعني إذا كانوا متحدين في نظام سياسي واحد،
one country, call it
يطلق عليه بلد واحد
"The United Street Sellers Republic," the U.S.S.R.,
"جمهو رية ولايات بائعي الشوارع " U.S.S.R
or "Bazaaristan,"
أو بازارستان
it would be worth 10 trillion dollars every year,
ستقدر قيمتها ب10 تريليون دولار كل عام،
and that would make it the second largest economy
والتي من شأنها أن تصبح ثاني أكبر اقتصاد.
in the world, after the United States.
في العالم بعد الولايات المتحدة
And given that projections are that the bulk
علما بأن التوقعات هي الجزء الأكبر
of economic growth over the next 15 years will come
من النموالاقتصادي على مدى السنوات ال 15 سيأتي
from emerging economies in the developing world,
من الاقتصادات الناشئة في العالم النامي،
it could easily overtake the United States
يمكنه بسهولة أن يتفوق على الولايات المتحدة
and become the largest economy in the world.
ويصبح أضخم اقتصاد على مستوى العالم
So the implications of that are vast, because it means
وبالتالي فإن الآثار المترتبة على ذلك واسعة جداً لأن ذلك يعني
that this is where employment is — 1.8 billion people —
أنه هناك حيث يوجد التوظيف - 1.8 مليار شخص
and this is where we can create a more egalitarian world,
وهذا هو المكان الذي يمكن أن نخلق فيه عالما أكثر مساواة،
because people are actually able to earn money and live
لأن الناس في الواقع قادرون على كسب المال وأن يعيشوا
and thrive, as Andrew Saboru did.
وينمو، كما فعل أندريو سابورو
Big businesses have recognized this,
وقد اعترفت الشركات الكبيرة بهذا،
and what's fascinating about this slide,
وما هو رائع في هذه الشريحة
it's not that the guys can carry boxes on their heads
ليس أن الرجال يمكن أن يحملوا صناديق على رؤوسهم
and run around without dropping them off.
والمشي بها دون أن تسقط منهم
it's that the Gala sausage roll is a product that's made
بل أن لفائف سجق غالا وهو منتج يصنع
by a global company called UAC foods
من قبل الشركة العالمية التي تدعى بـ UAC للغذاء
that's active throughout Africa and the Middle East,
التي تعتبر نشطة في جميع أنحاء أفريقيا والشرق الأوسط
but the Gala sausage roll is not sold in stores.
ولكن لا تباع لفائف سجق غالا في المتاجر
UAC foods has recognized that it won't sell if it's in stores.
شركة UAC للغذاء أدركت أنها لن تباع إن كانت في المتاجر
It's only sold by a phalanx of street hawkers
إنها تباع فقط من قبل كتيبة من الباعة المتجولين
who run around the streets of Lagos at bus stations
الذين يدورون في شوارع لاغوس في محطات الحافلات
and in traffic jams and sell it as a snack,
وفي الاختناقات المرورية وتباع كوجبة خفيفة،
and it's been sold that way for 40 years.
وقد تم بيعها على هذا النحو لمدة 40 عام.
It's a business plan for a corporation.
إنها خطة عمل للشركة
And it's not just in Africa.
وهي ليست فقط في أفريقيا
Here's Mr. Clean looking amorously at all the other
هنا "مستر كلين" ينظر لجميع الآخرين بحب
Procter &amp; Gamble products,
منتجات بروكتر أند غامبل
and Procter &amp; Gamble, you know,
وتعرفون بروكتر أند غامبل،
the statistic always cited is that Wal-Mart
الإحصائيات المشار إليها دائما هي تلك المرتبطة بوول مارت
is their largest customer, and it's true, as one store,
أنه أكبر عملائهم، وهذا صحيح، كمخزن واحد
Wal-Mart buys 15 percent, thus 15 percent
وول مارت يشتري 15 فالمئة، لذلك 15 فالمئة
of Procter &amp; Gamble's business is with Wal-Mart,
من شركة بروكتر أند غامبل هي مع وول مارت
but their largest market segment is something that they call
ولكن أكبر جزء من السوق لديهم هو الشي الذي يسمونه
"high frequency stores," which is all these tiny kiosks
"مخازن عالية التردد" والتي هي كل هذه الكشكات الصغيرة
and the lady in the canoe and all these other businesses
والسيدة في الزورق وجميع هذه الشركات الأخرى
that exist in System D, the informal economy,
التي توجد في النظام "د"، الاقتصاد الغير رسمي
and Procter &amp; Gamble makes 20 percent of its money
وشركة بروكتر أند غامبل تحصل على 20 بالمئة من أموالها
from that market segment,
من هذا الجزء من السوق
and it's the only market segment that's growing.
وهو الجزء الوحيد من السوق الذي ينمو
So Procter &amp; Gamble says, "We don't care whether a store
ولذلك بروكتر أند غامبل تقول "نحن لا نهتم ما إذا كان متجر
is incorporated or registered or anything like that.
غير مدرج أو مسجل أو أي شيء من هذا القبيل.
We want our products in that store."
نريد منتجاتنا في ذلك المتجر"
And then there's mobile phones.
ومن ثم هنالك الهواتف المتنقلة.
This is an ad for MTN,
هذا إعلان لـ MTN
which is a South African multinational
والتي هي شركة جنوب أفريقية متعددة الجنسيات
active in about 25 countries,
نشطة في 25 دولة تقريبا
and when they came into Nigeria —
وعندما جاؤوا إلى نيجيريا
Nigeria is the big dog in Africa.
نيجيريا هي الصيد الوافر في أفريقيا
One in seven Africans is a Nigerian,
واحد من كل سبعة أفارقة هو نيجيري
and so everyone wants in to the mobile phone market
وهكذا الكل يريد الدخول إلى سوق الهواتف المتنقلة
in Nigeria. And when MTN came in, they wanted
في نيجيريا. وعندما أتت MTN، أرادوا
to sell the mobile service like I get in the United States
أن يبيعوا خدمة التنقل كالتي أحصل عليها أنا في الولايات المتحدة
or like people get here in the U.K. or in Europe --
أو مثل ما يحصل الناس عليه هنا في بريطانيا أو في أوربا
expensive monthly plans, you get a phone,
الخطط الشهرية المكلفة، تحصل أنت على هاتف
you pay overages,
وتدفع الفائض
you're killed with fees --
فتقتل الرسوم --
and their plan crashed and burned.
فاحترقت خطتهم وتحطمت
And they went back to the drawing board, and they retooled,
ثم عادوا للوراء للوحة الرسم، وغيروا العتاد
and they came up with another plan:
وأتوا بخطة أخرى:
We don't sell you the phone,
نحن لن نبيعك الهاتف
we don't sell you the monthly plan.
نحن لن نبيع الخطة الشهرية
We only sell you airtime.
نحن فقط نبيعك الاستخدام
And where's the airtime sold?
وأين يباع الاستخدام؟
It's sold at umbrella stands all over the streets,
إنها تباع في مواقف المظلات في جميع أنحاء الشوارع
where people are unregistered, unlicensed,
حيث الناس غير مسجلين وغير مرخصين
but MTN makes most of its profits,
ولكن MNT تجني أكثر أرباحها
perhaps 90 percent of its profits,
ربما 90 بالمئة من أرباحها
from selling through System D, the informal economy.
من خلال البيع بنظام "د"، الاقتصاد الغير نظامي
And where do the phones come from?
ومن أين تأتي الهواتف؟
Well, they come from here. This is in Guangzhou, China,
حسنا، تأتي من هنا. هذه غوانغتشو، الصين
and if you go upstairs in this rather sleepy looking
وعندما تذهب للأعلى في المظهر المنعس
electronics mall, you find the Guangzhou Dashatou
مجمع إلكترونيات، ستجد قوانغتشو داشاتو
second-hand trade center,
سوق التجهيزات المستعمل التجاري
and if you go in there, you follow the guys with the muscles
وعندما تذهب إلى هناك، ستتبع الرجال المفتولين
who are carrying the boxes, and where are they going?
الذين يحملون الصناديق , وإلى أين هم ذاهبون؟
They're going to Eddy in Lagos.
إنهم ذاهبون الى إدي في لاغوس
Now, most of the phones there are not second-hand at all.
الآن، أغلب الهواتف ليست مستعملة إطلاقاً
The name is a misnomer.
الإسم توصيف خاطئ
Most of them are pirated. They have the name brand
أغلبها مقرصنة، ولها إسم تجاري
on them, but they're not manufactured by the name brand.
ولكنها ليست مصنعة بهذا الاسم التجاري
Now, are there downsides to that?
الآن، هل هناك سلبيات لذلك؟
Well, I guess. You know, China has no —
حسنا، أتوقع. تعرفون، الصين ليس لديها
(Laughter) — no intellectual property, right?
(ضحك) - ملكية فكرية، أليس كذلك؟
Versace without the vowels.
فيرساتشي دون حروف العلة.
Zhuomani instead of Armani.
زوماني بدلاً من أرماني
S. Guuuci, and -- (Laughter) (Applause)
إس غووووتشي - (ضحك) (تصفيق)
All around the world this is how products
في جميع أنحاء العالم هكذا يتم
are being distributed, so, for instance,
توزيع المنتجات، لذا، على سبيل المثال
in one street market on Rua 25 de Março
في شارع السوق رقم 1 في دي روا ماركو 25
in São Paulo, Brazil,
في ساوباولو، البرازيل
you can buy fake designer glasses.
يمكنك شراء نظارات مصممة مزيفة
You can buy cloned cologne.
يمكنك شراء كولونيا مستنسخة.
You can buy pirated DVDs, of course.
يمكنك شراء أقراص الفيديوالرقمية المقرصنة، بالطبع
You can buy New York Yankees caps
يمكنك شراء قبعات نيويورك يانكيز
in all sorts of unauthorized patterns.
في جميع أنواع الأنماط الغير المصرح بها.
You can buy cuecas baratas, designer underwear
يمكنك شراء ملابس داخلية من تصميم كواكيس باراتاس
that isn't really manufactured by a designer,
إنها ليست حقاً مصنعة من طرف مصمم
and even pirated evangelical mixtapes. (Laughter)
وحتى ميكس الأغاني الإنجيلية المقرصنة . (ضحك)
Now, businesses tend to complain about this,
الآن الشركات تميل الى تقديم شكوى حول هذا الموضوع
and their, they, I don't want to take away from their
وهناك، أنا لا أريد أن أمس
entire validity of complaining about it,
بمصداقية الشكوى من ذلك،
but I did ask a major sneaker manufacturer earlier this year
ولكني سألت مصانع أحذية رئيسية في وقت سابق من هذا العام
what they thought about piracy,
ما يعتقدونه حول القرصنة
and they told me, "Well, you can't quote me on this,
وأخبروني ، "حسنا, لا يمكنك الاقتباس مني
because if you quote me on this, I have to kill you,"
لأنك لواقتبست مني في هذا، فسيجب علي أن أقتلك"
but they use piracy as market research.
ولكنهم يستخدمون القرصنة كبحث تسويقي
The sneaker manufacturer told me that if
مصنعوا الأحذية أخبروني أنه إذا
they find that Pumas are being pirated, or Adidas
وجدوا أن بوماس تكون مقرصنة أوأديداس
are being pirated and their sneakers aren't being pirated,
تقرصن وأحذيتهم الرياضية لم تقرصن
they know they've done something wrong. (Laughter)
يعرفون بأنهم فعلوا شيء خاطئا (ضحك)
So it's very important to them to track piracy
لذلك إنه من المهم جداً لهم أن يتابعوا القرصنة
exactly because of this, and the people who are buying,
بالضبط بسبب هذا، والأشخاص الذين يشترون
the pirates, are not their customers anyway,
والمقرصنين، هم ليسوا عملاءهم لهم على أي حال
because their customers want the real deal.
لأن عملاءهم يريدون الشيء الحقيقي.
Now, there's another problem.
الآن، هناك مشكلة اخرى
This is a real street sign in Lagos, Nigeria.
هذه علامة شارع حقيقة في لاغوس، نيجيريا
All of System D really doesn't pay taxes, right?
كل نظام "د" لا يدفع الضرائب في الواقع، صحيح؟
And when I think about that, first of all I think that
وعندما أفكر في ذلك، أول شي أفكر في
government is a social contract between the people and
الحكومة هي عقد اجتماعي بين الناس
the government, and if the government isn't transparent,
والحكومة، وإذا كانت الحكومة ليست ذات شفافية
then the people aren't going to be transparent either,
فالناس لن يكونوا ذوي شفافية أيضاً
but also that we're blaming the little guy
ولكن نحن نلوم الرجل المتواضع
who doesn't pay his taxes, and we're not recognizing
الذي لا يدفع ضرائبه، ونحن لا ندرك
that everyone's fudging things all over the world,
أن الجميع يتنصل حول العالم
including some extremely respected businesses,
بمن في ذلك بعض الشركات المحترمة جدا،
and I'll give you one example.
وسأعطيكم مثالا واحدا،
There was one company that paid 4,000 bribes
هناك شركة دفعت 4000 رشوى
in the first decade of this millennium, and
في أول عقد من هذه الألفية،
a million dollars in bribes every business day, right?
مليون دولار في الرشاوى في كل عمل يوميا، صحيح؟
All over the world. And that company
حول العالم. وتلك الشركة
was the big German electronics giant Siemens.
كانت شركة الالكترونيات الكبرى سيمنز
So this goes on in the formal economy
لذا فإن هذا يذهب للاقتصاد الرسمي
as well as the informal economy,
كما هو حال الاقتصاد الرسمي
so it's wrong of us to blame — and I'm not singling out
لذا من الغلط أن نلوم - وأنا لن أفرد
Siemens, I'm saying everyone does it. Okay?
سيمنز، أنا أقول كل شخص يقوم بذلك. حسنا؟
I just want to end by saying that if Adam Smith
أنا أريد فقط أن أنهي بقول أن آدم سميث
had framed out a theory of the flea market
قد كوّن نظرية أسواق الشوارع
instead of the free market, what would be some
بدلاً من السوق الحرة، ما الذي قد تكون عليه
of the principles?
بعض المبادئ؟
First, it would be to understand that it could be
أولاً، سيكون فهم أنه يمكن أن تكون
considered a cooperative, and this is a thought
معتبرة كجمعية تعاونية، وهذا فكرة
from the Brazilian legal scholar Roberto Mangabeira Unger.
من الباحث القانوني البرازيلي روبرتو مانغابييرا أنغر.
Cooperative development is a way forward.
التطوير التعاوني هو الطريق نحو الأمام
Secondly, from the [Austrian] anarchist philosopher Paul Feyerabend,
ثانياً، من الفيلسوف (النمساوي) الفوضوي، باول فيرباند
facts are relative, and what is a massive right
الحقائق نسبية، وما هو صحيح
of self-reliance to a Nigerian businessperson
لرجل أعمال نيجيري معتمد على ذاته
is considered unauthorized and horrible to other people,
يعتبر غير مصرح ومروع لبعض البشر،
and we have to recognize that there are differences
وعلينا أن ندرك أن هناك اختلافات
in how people define things and what their facts are.
في كيفية تعريف الناس للأشياء وما هي حقائقهم
And third is, and I'm taking this from
والثالث هو، وقد أخذت هذه من
the great American beat poet Allen Ginsberg,
الشاعر الأمريكي الكبير واللامع ألين جينسبيرج
that alternate economies barter and
أن اقتصادات المقايضة البديلة
different kinds of currency, alternate currencies
والنوعيات المختلفة من العملات، والعملات البديلة
are also very important, and he talked about
هي أيضاً مهمة جداً، وكان يتحدث عن
buying what he needed just with his good looks.
شراء ما يحتاجه فقط بشكله الجميل.
And so I just want to leave you there, and say that
ولذلك فإني فقط أريد أن أترككم هناك، وأقول أن
this economy is a tremendous force for global development
هذا الاقتصاد هو قوة هائلة للتنمية عالمية
and we need to think about it that way.
وعلينا أن نفكر به بتلك الطريقة
Thank you very much. (Applause)
شكراً جزيلاً لكم ( تصفيق)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)